{
  "reference_number": "12677",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "There is NO more time to delay. We must make solid commitments now. I call on all members of Parliament to work together to create\n\n a consensus: a non-partisan commitment to a legally-binding long term target via this Act."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "All greenhouse gases, including methane, must be significantly reduced. New Zealand should take a science-based approach to\n ensure our emission reduction efforts are as effective as possible. Take \"science-based approach\" to mean minimising cumulative\n emissions and gross emissions and distinguishing between long and short-lived greenhouse gases. We must urgently minimise our\n\n cumultative emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The 2050 target should only be revised following a significant change in scientific knowledge or international law (such as the Paris\n\n Agreement becoming more ambitious). Any revision should require input from the Climate Change Commission and approval by\n Parliament."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes. It is important that three budgets are in effect at all time. This is a cornerstone principle of the Act."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "We have to move beyond partisan politics; NZ cannot afford to flip flop on this issue as governments change. It is inappropriate for an\n incoming government to reduce the targets or effectiveness of a budget already set."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Only under exceptional circumstances that cannot be predicted, such as natural disaster. Changes should require the input of the\nClimate Change Commission and be approved by Parliament."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The emission budget must allow a fair, cost-effective, environmentally sustainable pathway to the 2050 target."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Within six months of the budget being set."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Government policy must be fair, cost-effective, environmentally sustainable and comprehensive. It must also honour and uphold Te\nTiriti o Waitangi."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, I support the CCC having dual functions: providing advice AND monitoring progress and holding successive governments to\n\naccount. It should not make decisions itself because it is not accountable to the public and its members are not democratically\nelected. Neither can it be its own watchdog."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Generally yes but note that public health is also an important area of expertise."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Absolutely. NZ's adapation response is very important and the CCC's expertise should contribute to our planning and response."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I am in favour of the Government preparing a national climate risk assessment, and a national policy plan to address these risks."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I favour a mandatory adaption reporting power."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I wish to tautoko the comprehensive and thoughtful submission made to the Ministry by Generation Zero. In particular, I want to\n\nhighlight their points about Te Tiriti: \"Zero Carbon Act must honour Te Tiriti o Waitangi by giving effect to meaningful partnership\nbetween iwi and the Crown. The Zero Carbon Act’s targets and policies must be made consistently with the tino rangatiratanga of iwi\n\nand hapū, as enshrined in Te Tiriti.\" Please note, I am happy for the Ministry to publish my name and submission but do NOT consent\nto the publication of my email address in any public forum. My email is provided only for the purpose of being contacted by the\n\nMinistry in regard to this submission."
    }
  ]
}
